So today's דף daf is כ"ה. chaf hay. We're going to pick
up four lines from the top, the part that we read, we
did very quickly at the end of yesterday. So we have a
debate of ריש לקיש Reish Lakish and רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, what
is this הלכה halacha that if a נזיר Nazir dies or the
husband annuls the vow, and there's money that has been sanctified and
set aside for the קרבנות korbanot and it's not specified which, that
it all gets used for an עולה. olah. And the גמרא Gemara
assumes that the case here is that it's assumed that the money,
this pile, was going to go to all of the קרבנות korbanot
including a חטאת. chatas. So it's a particular חידוש. chidush. It's not
like it could have all gone to an עולה. olah. Some of
it had to go to a חטאת. chatas. And nevertheless the הלכה
halacha is that it gets to all go to an עולה olah
once it cannot be used for the נזיר Nazir purposes. So
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said it's a הלכה למשה מסיני. Halacha le-Moshe
mi-Sinai. ריש לקיש Reish Lakish learns it from a פסוק. pasuk. So
the גמרא Gemara says the following.
בשלמא לרבי יוחנן Bishlama le-Rabbi Yochanan דאמר הלכה היא בנזיר. da'amar halacha
hi be-nazir. So according to רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan it's all הלכה,
halacha, אטו הא הכא סתומיים מפורשים לאו. atu ha hacha stumiyim mefurashim
lav. So therefore okay, it's a הלכה, halacha, it has arbitrary rules,
we can't ask any questions. The הלכה halacha is that if the
pile has been non-designated,
you know, then that's when you get to use it for an
עולה. olah. If the things have been designated, this is a pile
for חטאת, chatas, this is for an עולה, olah, this is for
שלמים, shlamim, then the הלכה halacha wasn't said and you do with
each pile what you're supposed to do.
אלא לריש לקיש, Ella le-Reish Lakish, but according to ריש לקיש Reish
Lakish who learns it from a פסוק, pasuk, לכל נדריהם ולכל נדבתם,
le-chol nidreihem u-le-chol nidvosem, for all of their נדרים nedarim and for
all of their נדבות, nedavos, and for that he learned that something
that basically started as a נדר neder like נזירות nezirut which begins
as a נדר neder and then somehow there's leftover funds you use
it towards a נדבה nidava which is understood to represent a full
gift, an עולה olah which is fully given over. So that's like
the paradigmatic נדבה. nidava. So if that's true that that's the פסוק,
pasuk, so מאי איריא סתומים? mai irya stumim? Why would it only
be by a pile of money that's been non-designated?
אפילו מפורשים, afilla mefurashim, even if it's been designated. It's money that
started off for a נדר, neder, is leftover essentially, can't be used
for its intended purpose because the נזיר Nazir died or it was
the husband annulled the נזירות. nezirut. And now let's just use it
for a נדבה, nidava, maybe even if the money was explicitly designated
as such. So the גמרא Gemara says אמר רבא, Amar Rava, no,
מפורשים לא מצית אמרת. mefurashim lo matzis amart. No, no, no. If
the money has been specifically designated, you can't repurpose it. That we
haven't, we know already there's a principle that leftover funds for a
particular purpose stay within the category that they've been designated. How do
you know this? כבר פסקה תנא דבי רבי ישמעאל. Kvar paska tana
de-vei Rabbi Yishmael. It's learned from the ברייתא braita of רבי ישמעאל.
Rabbi Yishmael. רק קדשיך אשר יהיו לך ונדריך תשא ובאת אל המקום
אשר יבחר ה'. Rak kodashecha asher yihyu lecha u-nedarecha tisa u-vasa el
hamakom asher yivchar Hashem. That's the פסוק. pasuk. The sacrifices that you
have and your vows you should lift up and bring to the
place where God where God has chosen. And the end of the
פסוק pasuk is ועשית עלתיך הבשר והדם על מזבח ה' אלהיך ודם
זבחיך ישפך על יסוד מזבח ה' והבשר תאכל. Ve-asisa olotecha habasar vehadam
al mizbe'ach Hashem Elokecha vedam zevachecha yishapech al yesod mizbach Hashem v'habasar
tochel. Okay, so and you should bring your you know your ועשית
עלתיך, olotecha, your burnt sacrifices and so on and for the שלמים
shlamim you eat their meat. So that's like a general פסוק pasuk
that says you bring your קרבנות korbanot to the בית המקדש. Beis
Hamikdash. The point of this מדרש הלכה midrash halacha though is that
you know there's enough other פסוקים pesukim that say you bring your
קרבנות korbanot to the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. So this has to
be telling you something else. So what else is this telling you?
So רק קדשיך אשר יהיו לך ונדריך, Rak kodashecha asher yihyu lecha
u-nedarecha, so that's not your normal קרבנות, korbanot, that's something else that's
sanctified. בוולדי קדשים ובתמורתם הכתוב מדבר. Bevladei kodashim u-vitmurasam hakatuv medaber. A
child of a sacrifice, so you have some female animals and you
sanctified them and then they gave birth. So that's sort of a
derivative type of a קדושה. kedusha. Or a תמורה, tmura, you said
this animal is in exchange for this and as we know you're
not allowed to do that and if you do it the second
animal becomes sanctified and the first one retains its sanctity. So all
of those are things that are not just your classic sacrifices but
a certain amount of a derivative קדושה. kedusha. And even those it
says what do you do with a תמורה tmura and what do
you do with a ולד? vlad? So you might have thought like
I don't know maybe you're stuck like it can't it wasn't the
original קדושה, kedusha, maybe you have to let it graze and redeem
it. How do you know what you're supposed to do with a
ולד vlad and a תמורה? tmura? So this פסוק pasuk tells you
no, you can bring those as sacrifices as well. So what do
you do with them? So
that are not the original קדושה. kedusha. תשא ובאת אל המקום אשר
יבחר ה'. Tisa u-vasa el hamakom asher yivchar Hashem. Bring them to
the place God has chosen. So okay, so maybe you bring them
up to the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash and then you don't do
anything with them. יכול יעלם לבית הבחירה וימנע מהם מים ומזון בשביל
שימותו? Yachol ya'alem le-veit habechira ve-yimna mehem mayim u-mazon bi-shvil she-yamusu?
Maybe you bring them up to the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash and
you let them die there, which would be pretty ironic. No, תלמוד
לומר talmud lomar at the end of the פסוק pasuk says ועשית
עלתיך הבשר והדם. ve-asisa olotecha habasar vehadam.
So you should actually bring your sacrifices. Okay, למה לך? Loma lecha?
So that tells you that you have these derivative קדושות. kedushot. What
do you do? You bring them as their original קדושה kedusha would
have been brought. So כדי לומר לך kdei lomar lecha to tell
you כדרך שאתה נוהג בעולה נוהג בתמורתה. ke-derech she-ata noheg ba-olah noheg
bi-tmurata.
The same thing you would do the עולה olah do with its
exchange.
כדרך שאתה נוהג בשלמים נוהג בוולדיהם. ke-derech she-ata noheg bi-shlamim noheg bi-vladeihem.
Deal with the child of the שלמים. shlamim. Now why do they
give the example of תמורה tmura for an עולה olah and a
ולד vlad for a שלמים? shlamim? Quick quiz.
Why?
עולה olah, *olah* has to be a male.
A male, right! So right. עולה olah *olah* has to be a
male. אם עולה ola קרבנו מן הזכר *im olah korbano min ha-zachar*.
And a שלמים shlamim, *shlamim* can be a male or a female.
So you could have a תמורה tmurah שלמים shlamim *tmurah shlamim*, but
you cannot have a ולד vlad עולה ola. *vlad olah*. So since
we're giving the example of a ולד Vlad, *vlad* by a שלמים
shlamim *shlamim*, we're going to give the example of a תמורה Tmurah,
*tmurah* by an עולה ola, *olah*. Alright, so anyway, so either one,
ועשית עלותיך הבשר והדם v'asita olotecha habasar v'hadam. *v'asita olotecha habasar v'hadam*,
ודם זבחיך *v'dam zvachecha*—זבחיך *zvachecha* is a שלמים shlamim *shlamim*, right?—ודם זבחיך
ישפך על מזבח ה' אלוהיך והבשר תאכל *v'dam zvachecha yishafeich al mizbeiach
Hashem elokecha v'habasar tochel*. And you eat the meat of the שלמים
shlamim *shlamim*. Okay, מזבח ה' אלוהיך *mizbeiach Hashem elokecha*, thank you. Okay,
so that's what we learn, that what you do with those is
that you bring them in the way that they've been, that their
original קדושה kedusha, *kedusha* has been designated. Now, יכול אף ולד חטאת
ותמורת אשם כן Yachol af vlad chatat u'tmurat asham ken. *yachol af
vlad chatat u-tmurat asham kein*? How about the child of a חטאת
chatat. *chatat*—חטאת chatat *chatat* is again female—or the תמורה tmura, *tmurah* of
an אשם asham *asham*—an אשם asham *asham* is male, so you can't
have a ולד vlad, *vlad* there—maybe even those derivative קדושות *kedushot* you
also bring them as קרבנות korbanot, *korbanot*? תלמוד לומר *talmud lomar*: רק
קדשיך rak kodshecha, *rak kodashecha*. Not all of them. In fact, it'd
be true that the פסוקים *psukim* are talking basically about an עולה
ola. *olah* and a שלמים shelamim *shlamim*. They're not talking about a
חטאת chatat, *chatat* and an אשם asham *asham*. דברי רבי ישמעאל Rabbi
Ishmael *divrei Rabbi Yishmael*, that's what רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael. *Rabbi Yishmael*
says. Because as we know—we'll talk about אשם asham, *asham* in a
minute—but as we know, certainly by a חטאת chatat. *chatat*, if it's
not the original קדושה kedusha? *kedusha*, if it's—I mean if it's not—if
it can't be used for its intended purpose (the owner died, they
were atoned for with another, or it was the child of a
חטאת chatat *chatat*), so it's not the original things that were sanctified.
In all those cases, the animal has to be let die. You
cannot bring it as a קרבן korban, חטאת chatat *korban chatat*. חטאת
chatat. *chatat* is very much the concrete function, it's specific, and it
cannot have any function outside of that. Okay, so that's what רבי
ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael. *Rabbi Yishmael* learns. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva אומר אינו
צריך *Rabbi Akiva omeir eino tzarich*. You don't need to learn it
from the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* תשא ובאת tisa uvata. *tisa u-vata* and
from all of these like, you know, have a whole פרשה *parsha*
in the תורה Torah, *Torah* talking about that, or maybe from the
word רק rak *rak*, excuse me, to exclude a חטאת chatat, *chatat*
and an אשם asham *asham*. הרי הוא אומר *harei hu omeir*, the
פסוק pasuk *pasuk* says: אשם הוא asham hu *asham hu*. It is
an אשם asham *asham*. From a different פסוק pasuk *pasuk*, not by
here, what's talking about an אשם asham? *asham*. בהווייתו יהא *ba-havayato yehei*.
It doesn't leave its status of being an אשם asham *asham*. It
cannot serve any other function. Okay, now it's not exactly clear why
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva *Rabbi Akiva* prefers a פסוק pasuk *pasuk* אשם
הוא asham hu. *asham hu* to a פסוק pasuk *pasuk* of רק
rak *rak*. Either way, you're learning it, I don't know, from an
extra word. It doesn't seem easy to fit this into a classic,
you know, רבי ישמעאל *Rabbi Yishmael*-רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva, *Rabbi Akiva* debate
where רבי ישמעאל *Rabbi Yishmael* is learning the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* in
a more natural way than רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva *Rabbi Akiva*. Anyway,
maybe רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva *Rabbi Akiva* though is saying is that
רק *rak* is a little generic. It's not clear what it's excluding.
אשם הוא asham hu. *asham hu* is specifically by an אשם asham,
*asham* and telling you the אשם asham *asham* retains its identity, cannot
somehow be used in any other type of a function. Anyway, what
you see from this is, to get back to our point before
we further unpack this, is this פסוק pasuk? *pasuk* tells you that
some type of derivative קדושה kedusha *kedusha*, ולד velad, *vlad*, תמורה tmura,
*tmurah*, etc., is used the same way as the original קדושה Kedusha
*kedusha*. So if it came from an עולה ola, *olah*, it's used
as an עולה ola, *olah*. If it came from a שלמים shelamim
*shlamim*, it's used from a שלמים shelamim, *shlamim*. And therefore, our assumption
is is that the same would be true in any type of
a case if something has a clear category and a designation. So
just because ריש לקיש Reish Lakish, *Reish Lakish* learns from this פסוק
pasuk, *pasuk* לכל נדריהם ולכל נדבותם *l'chol nidreihem u-l'chol nidvotham* that somehow
money gets repurposed as an עולה ola. *olah*, we're saying that could
never have been possible if the money already was clearly designated. Like,
we know that something that has a קדושה kedusha *kedusha* that's been
designated, it stays in that category. Okay, so if the money has
been set aside as an עולה Olah. *olah*, then the guy died,
it's going to be used as an עולה Olah *olah*, no different
than if the animal had a—was a תמורה tmura, *tmurah* or whatever.
You know, if the money was set aside as a שלמים shelamim.
*shlamim* and the guy died or the נזירות nezirut. *nezirut* was annulled,
it's going to be used as a שלמים shelamim *shlamim*. If it's
going to be a חטאת chatat *chatat* and he died, it's like
this חטאת chatat, *chatat* that gave birth to a—to a baby, and
what do you do with it? You don't bring it, you let
it die. You do the same thing, you know, if it can't
be used at that original purpose, you let it die. Those are
categories we know. So if the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* is still telling
you something that started as a נדר *neder*, meaning נזירות *nezirut* or
whatever, becomes a נדבה *nedava*, becomes an עולה Olah. *olah*, the only
case it could be talking about is a pile of unspecified moneys.
That type of a thing, because it's not specified and we don't
know exactly what to do with it, that the פסוק pasuk *pasuk*
can tell us, oh, that's the חידוש chiddush *chiddush* of the פסוק
pasuk *pasuk* is you use that as an עולה Olah *olah*. And
again, part of the big חידוש Chiddush *chiddush* there is even though
תוספות Tosfos *Tosafot* is saying, like, you know, sounds a little from
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, תוספות Tosfos *Tosafot* makes it clear, that even
though it was clear that from that pile was going to come
all three קרבנות Korbanos, *korbanot*, so some money from that pile was
going to be used for a חטאת chatat, *chatat* and a שלמים
shelamim, *shlamim*, nevertheless, because it's not specified, the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* is
telling you it all gets to be used as an עולה Olah.
*olah*. Yes?
What—why couldn't you ask the same קשיא *kashya* to רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan* and say and say that no, it's become מפורשים
*meforashim* because of this לימוד *limmud*?
You could, but the point is you don't need to go to
the לימוד *limmud*. It's all הלכה למשה מסיני halacha l'moshe misinai, *halacha
l'Moshe mi-Sinai*. So we can't even ask any questions. He could just
tell us it was set in
this—as a הלכה למשה מסיני halacha l'moshe misinai, *halacha l'Moshe mi-Sinai*, there's
no—it's all arbitrary.
No distinctions? No, it's the opposite point. It's the point is that
you can't any ask any logical questions about it. It's all—it's all
an arbitrary rule. So if he's telling us the arbitrary rule says
in case—in cases of A, B, C, and D, when it has
these criteria, this is what you do with it, we can't say,
well, why not in this other case? What do you mean why
not in this other case? That's a special rule, it's a special
exception. It's said for this concrete narrow circumstances, end of story. But
with ריש לקיש you could ask a type of a logical question.
Why should it apply to one type of scenario and not another?
So we need to show, no, there's reasons why it doesn't apply
to other scenarios. Alright, so now the גמרא Gemara says, now we're
going to unpack this. Okay,
תני, Tani, so we taught, like let's go back and look at
this ברייתא Braita now that we've sort of finished with our ריש
לקיש, רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan and we understand this idea of מושב
סתומים. moshav setumim. Okay, תני, Tani, יכול יעלה לבית הבחירה וימנע מהם
מים ומזון. Yachol ya'aleh l'veit habechirah v'yimna mehem mayim u'mazon.
If you have this תמורה or ולד velad, of a קרבן, korban
maybe you bring him up to the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash and
just let it die before you got to the end of the
פסוק pasuk where it says ועשית עולותיך, v'asita olotecha, where it just
said תשא ובאת. tisa uvata, So the גמרא Gemara says ושימותו. v'sheyamutu.
So the גמרא Gemara says, אמאי? Amai? ולד חטאת ותמורתה למיתה. Vlad
chatat u'tmuratah l'mitah.
One minute. This idea that you let an animal die, that's a
special הלכה למשה מסיני, halacha l'moshe misinai a special tradition that we
have by the child of a חטאת. chatat. Okay, by that, you
know, חטאת chatat, that can't be brought, we have to let die.
And by the way, this issue came up yesterday. What do you
do with them? And I said, yeah, you starve them to death.
And here, basically, that's what this is saying. וימנע מהם מים ומזון.
V'yimna mehem mayim u'mazon. You withhold food and water, like all of
us today. Okay, haha. Anyway,
hopefully we won't have the same end, right? Anyway, you withhold from
them food and water. That's what you do by a חטאת, chatat,
you starve it and you let it die. Okay, but the גמרא
Gemara says, so you don't need a פסוק pasuk to tell me
don't do that by an עולה ושלמים olah u'shlamim that isn't the
original one. Because I of course I know, I don't need a
פסוק pasuk because I know that the הלכה halacha tells me do
it by a חטאת. chatat So somehow I would know that that
tradition that says this is what you do by a חטאת chatat
that can't be brought in the way it was intended, I can
infer that I don't do it by anything else. Again, somehow once
we're in this area of הלכה למשה מסיני, halacha l'moshe misinai we
sort of learn that every הלכה למשה מסיני halacha l'moshe misinai is
essentially like an exception. Okay, telling me this narrow concrete case, this
is what this הלכה למשה מסיני halacha l'moshe misinai was said for.
So since by a חטאת chatas there's like this הלכה למשה מסיני
halacha l'moshe misinai. that you let it die, so clearly I know
that, you know, it doesn't apply by other things. It's clearly a
דין din by a חטאת. chatas So why do I need the
פסוק pasuk to tell me not to do it by these other
things? So the גמרא Gemara said, no, אילו לא קרא, ilu lo
kra, if it wasn't for the end of the פסוק pasuk. ועשית
עולותיך הבשר והדם, v'asita olotecha habasar v'hadam, הוה אמינא, hava amina, I
would have thought ולד חטאת בכל מקום. vlad chatat bechol makom. Yeah,
maybe by the child of a חטאת, chatas a חטאת chatas. that
I can't bring for its intended purpose, I let it die, I
starve it to death wherever it will be. But ולדי קדשים, vladay
kodashim, but these other קרבנות, Korbanos, the עולה, Olah the שלמים, shelamim,
בבית הבחירה, beveit habechirah, that's תשא ובאת, I have to bring it
up to the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash and let it die there.
What a crazy הוה אמינא. hava amina. Anyway, alright, so I still
might have thought, yes, it's a special rule by חטאת, chatas but
that's that you let it die everywhere. Maybe this פסוק pasuk is
telling me by these other things, bring them up and let them
die in the בית המקדש. Beit Hamikdash. קא משמע לן דלא. Ka
mashma lan d'lo. Okay, so it tells me no, bring it up
to the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash and actually bring it as a
sacrifice. Fine, that was a little crazy הוה אמינא. hava amina. Moving
on. תני, Tani, let's keep on going. יכול אף ולד חטאת vlad
chatat, ותמורת אשם asham כן. It goes on to say maybe this
idea
that this is what you do with an עולה Olah. or שלמים
Shelamim? that are derivative קדושה, kedusha not the original sort of use,
you can go ahead and bring it as a קרבן korban, regardless.
Maybe it's that I would do the same with a child of
a חטאת, chatas. also bring it as a קרבן, korban. right? And
then it says רק or רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says אשם הוא
asham hu by an אשם asham and presumably it's the same by
a חטאת. chatas תלמוד לומר רק. Talmud lomar rak. So the גמרא
Gemara is going to have a very similar question. למה לי קרא?
Lama li kra? הלכתא גמירי לה. Hilchata g'miri lah. Why do you
need a פסוק? pasuk We have הלכה למשה מסיני halacha l'moshe misinai.
to tell you that by a חטאת, chatas. you don't do this
with a חטאת, Chatas like we just referred to a minute ago.
הלכתא גמירי לה ולד חטאת למיתה אזלא, Hilchata g'miri lah vlad chatat
l'mitah azla, that the child of a חטאת Chatas has to die
because it can't be brought. By the way, the five cases of
a חטאת Chatas that cannot be used for its original purpose
are, the mnemonic is ותמנע, Vitmanah, ותמנע היתה פילגש. Vitmanah haytah pilegesh.
So
it's ולד חטאת, Chatas תמורת
חטאת, tmurat chatat, מתו בעליה, נתכפרו באחר. metu ba'aleha nitkapru be-acher, And
what's the last one? ולד, מתו, metu, נתכפרו באחר. nitkapru b'acher. אבודה?
Avudah? Passed its year?
No, that would be נזירות. Yeah, but that's not the normal case.
תמורה, ולד, מתו, metu, נתכפרו
באחר, nitkapru b'acher. it'll come to me, עברה שנתה. avrah shnatah. Oh,
when it's more than a year old. Okay, so anyway, those are
the five cases. Alright, so anyway, okay, so we know that that's
הלכה למשה מסיני. halacha l'Moshe m'Sinai And of course the simple sense
of this is, maybe not everybody agrees that it's הלכה למשה מסיני.
halacha l'Moshe m'Sinai Maybe according to רבי ישמעאל and רבי עקיבא they're
learning it from this פסוק, pasuk? even from the פסוק pasuk of
רק or from the פסוק pasuk of אשם הוא. asham hu. They're
learning that you don't bring it as a קרבן. korban Now how
do you know if you don't bring it as a קרבן korban?
and you do starve it and you let it die? I mean,
what other options are there for it if you can't bring it
as a קרבן? korban Maybe you could have said that you wait
till it gets a מום mum and you redeem it, but I
mean okay, but once it's you know... Or you could say, yeah,
maybe that's sort of built on, that's sort of logically the next
step once the פסוק pasuk *posuk* is telling me I don't have
an option of bringing it. Then if I can't bring it, then
why should redeeming it be any better than the ולד חטאת Chatas
*vlad chatas* or the תמורת חטאת Chatas *tmuras chatas*? If I can't
bring the thing that's not the original thing when it's not serving
its original function, maybe it's just obvious that I have to let
it die. Somehow this גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is very, this גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* and a lot of other גמרות *Gemoras* are very committed to
the idea that the idea that a חטאת Chatas *chatas* dies is
a הלכה למשה מסיני halacha l'Moshe m'Sinai *halacha l'Moshe miSinai*. And therefore
they say why, why are we learning it from a פסוק pasuk.
*posuk*? But again, you see from the very fact that this מדרש
הלכה halacha, *midrash halacha* had a הווא אמינא *hava amina* that you
would let the עולה Olah *olah* and the שלמים Shelamim. *shelamim* die
if they're not the original one, you see that the simple sense
of this מדרש הלכה halacha *midrash halacha* is, if the
פסוק *posuk* is either telling me I'm allowed to bring it when
it's not the original one, and if that's not the option, then
presumably it's telling me I have to let it die. Right? So
the simple sense is that this מדרש הלכה Halacha *midrash halacha* is
learning the idea that a חטאת Chatas *chatas* of ולד חטאת Chatas
*vlad chatas* dies implicitly from the fact that the פסוק *posuk* is
telling me it can't be brought. Nevertheless, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is
committed to the idea that that's a הלכה למשה מסיני halacha l'Moshe
m'Sinai *halacha l'Moshe miSinai*. And therefore it wants to know why do
I need this פסוק *posuk* if I already know it from a
הלכה למשה מסיני halacha le-moshe mi-sinai, *halacha l'Moshe miSinai*?
That was about why, what would be the הווא אמינא *hava amina*
that you would let the עולה Olah. *olah* and the שלמים *shelamim*
die if we obviously know it's only by a חטאת Chatas, *chatas*?
And the answer is, and the answer, no, there was like why
do I need to tell me by עולה Olah. *olah* and שלמים
*shelamim* if I already know it by חטאת Chatas *chatas*? I mean,
what's the הווא אמינא *hava amina* by עולה Olah *olah* and שלמים
*shelamim*? The answer is the הווא אמינא *hava amina* would have been
they have to die in the בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash*. Here the
question is why do I need to tell me the הלכה halacha
*halacha* that a חטאת chatas *chatas* dies that can't be used if
I already know that הלכה halacha *halacha* from a הלכה halacha למשה
מסיני *halacha l'Moshe miSinai*?
Yeah, that means that the בבלי *Bavli*'s agenda is to move away
from the authority of a מדרש הלכה halacha *midrash halacha*.
No, I wouldn't
say, yeah, I know, I know, but I wouldn't say that, I
would not generalize it like that. You know, yeah, because in general,
it's not like it says we'd rather learn something from a הלכה
halacha למשה מסיני *halacha l'Moshe miSinai* from a פסוק *posuk*. It's just
saying that in this case it's committed to the idea that this
הלכה *halacha* we know from a הלכה למשה מסיני *halacha l'Moshe miSinai*.
Okay? If it were just up in the air, right, it could
have said, well why do I need a הלכה למשה מסיני *halacha
l'Moshe miSinai*, I have it from a פסוק *posuk*? You know? So
it's not like in principle it seems הלכה למשה מסיני *halacha l'Moshe
miSinai* is better. It's just that particularly by this הלכה *halacha* that
there are חמש חטאות המתות *chameish chatous hamessos*, it's committed to the
idea that we know this as a הלכה למשה מסיני *halacha l'Moshe
miSinai*. So it doesn't want to say that we're getting it from
this פסוק *posuk*.
And which תמורות *tmuros* are you allowed to let it stay and
then you redeem it if it gets a blemish?
Not a חטאת chatas *chatas*. You can't do anything as a תמורה
*tmura*. You can bring every תמורה *tmura* that's not a תמורת חטאת
chatas *tmuras chatas* as a קרבן Korban *korban* or an אשם asham
*asham*, but you're not allowed to make a תמורה *tmura*. But if
an animal gets a מום *mum*, you're allowed to redeem it on
money and then use the money to go ahead and to buy
a different קרבן Korban *korban*. That's not a תמורה *tmura* because you're
redeeming it on money, you're not exchanging it for another קרבן Korban,
*korban* directly. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this, okay,
למה לי קרא הלכתא גמירי לה חמש חטאות דמיתו אזלו *lama li
kra hilchasa gemiri la chameish chatous damisu azlu*. So we know this
is a הלכה למשה מסיני *halacha l'Moshe miSinai*. Why does it seem
like this is what exactly is what the פסוק *posuk* is teaching
us? So the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* says הכי נמי hachi nami, יהא
רעית *hachi nami yehei ra'is*, we do know it as a הלכה
למשה מסיני *halacha l'Moshe miSinai*. דקרא לאשם הוא דאתא *dikra l'asham hu
da'asa*. But what we don't know is what's the הלכה *halacha* by
an אשם *asham*, that an אשם *asham* you also are not allowed
to bring if it's like a תמורת אשם *tmuras asham*, it's not
the original thing that can't be brought for the original purpose. So
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, now אשם נמי הלכתא גמירי לה *asham
nami hilchasa gemiri la*. One minute, that's part of our הלכה למשה
מסיני *halacha l'Moshe miSinai*. What's our הלכה למשה מסיני *halacha l'Moshe miSinai*?
כל שבחטאת מתה באשם רועה *kol shebachatas mesa be'asham ro'eh*. The הלכה
למשה מסיני *halacha l'Moshe miSinai* is that anything that by a חטאת
chatas, *chatas* you would let die, by an אשם *asham* which is
very similar, it's חטא *cheit*-related, but somehow we always assume, actually there's
a position, there's one of the תנאים *Tannaim* says that it is
exactly like a חטאת chatas, *chatas*, but we always say that it's
a little bit different, it's not as weighty but it's very similar.
So by the אשם *asham* the הלכה *halacha* is you can't bring
it as a קרבן korban *korban*.
What you do is you wait for, you allow it to graze.
And what do you do when you allow it to graze? Big
deal. So when you allow it to graze then when it gets
a blemish you redeem the value and you bring with it not
an אשם *asham* because again if it wasn't the original אשם *asham*
was sanctified for, it cannot be brought, nothing else can be brought.
So what you do though is you redeem it and you bring
it as an עולה Olah *olah*. So that's an interesting הלכה *halacha*
like this unspecified title, somehow there's this הלכה *halacha* that you redeem
it, you wait for it to get a blemish, you redeem the
value and then you go ahead and you use that money for
an עולה Olah. *olah*. Now by the way, just because what I
said was a little imprecise, if the אשם *asham* has not like
if the אשם *asham* can still be used for its original purpose,
let's say I sanctify an animal as an אשם *asham* and it
got a blemish before I brought it as a קרבן *korban*, then
fine, the same is true by an אשם *asham* or חטאת chatas
*chatas*, if it still can be used for its original purpose you
redeem it, you buy another animal and that becomes the original אשם
*asham*, it becomes the original חטאת chatas *chatas*. But in a case
where it cannot be used for its original purpose, it's a תמורה
*tmura*, the owner's brought another קרבן *korban*, the owner's died, whatever the
case might be, it can't be used for its original purpose, for
a חטאת chatas *chatas* getting a blemish doesn't matter, it has this
קדושה *kedusha*, this can never be used. for something other than its
original purpose, so it has to be let die, whereas by an
אשם, the חידוש Chiddush is that even though it can't be used
for that original purpose, in this it can be transferred into an
עולה Olah, if the animal gets a
blemish. Okay?
Dvorah Kesten? No. Just meant to say an אשם and a חטאת
chatas were effectively the same, and yet.
Right, not exactly the same. Right, so that's what I said. There
is a תנא tanna that says exactly the same, but this is
saying not that way, yeah.
If the animal for a חטאת chatas, or for an אשם gets
a blemish before I bring it, right? So I redeem it, I
get another animal and I bring that instead. That first one loses
its קדושה? Yep. I can have lamb chops for dinner.
Yeah. Well, yes. I mean, there's certain things you can't do with
it, like you can't graze it and work it, but yes, you
can shecht it and eat it.
Like for business purposes?
But you can shecht it and eat it. That's certainly true. Yes.
Okay. All right. So now the גמרא Gemara. says, so we also
know the, so you can't tell me the פסוק is telling you
an אשם, that's part of the הלכה למשה מסיני that it grazes
and then, if it can't be used, it grazes and then eventually
it becomes an עולה. olah So אלא, ela, so the גמרא Gemara
says, fine. מהלכתא הוה אמינא הלכתא והיא אקריביה לא ליחייב עליה. Mehilchata
hava amina hilchata vi-hee akriveh lo lichayev aleh.
You're right. But if it was just for the הלכה, I would
have thought, fine, there's a הלכה that says you have to bring,
you have to let this חטאת chatas. die. But let's say I
went ahead, I brought the חטאת. chatas No, so I would have
thought that maybe I didn't do the right thing with it, but
I wouldn't have thought that I somehow transgressed a פסוק in the
תורה, like I wouldn't have transgressed a positive or negative command. לא
ליחייב עליה ולא כלום. lo lichayev aleh v'lo klum.
So קמשמע לן קרא, ka mashma lan kra, so the פסוק is
telling me דמקרב ליה קאים עליה בעשה. d'makrav leh ka'im aleh b'aseh.
You actually transgress a positive command. What's the positive command? This is
all for not רבי עקיבא, but for רבי ישמעאל. It says ועשית
עלותיך הבשר והדם. It says רק קדשיך אשר יהיו לך ונדריך. rak
kodshecha asher yihyu lecha u'nedarecha.
Only your קדשיך, kodshecha, only your עולות olot and שלמים can you
bring as a קרבן if somehow it's not the original one. But
a חטאת chatas is not included. So basically it's an implicit prohibition
that derives from a positive, right? It's a לאו הבא מכלל עשה.
lav haba m'klal aseh. Only for your עולות olot and שלמים can
you bring them, implicitly not your חטאת. chatas, So if you were
to have brought your חטאת chatas in this circumstance, you would have
violated the עשה. aseh. So the הלכה למשה מסיני tells me that
it can't be brought, it's not כשר kasher if it's brought in
this case, and this פסוק tells me that I violated an עשה.
aseh. That's how we solved it for רבי ישמעאל. But we're not
done, because רבי עקיבא doesn't learn it from an עשה. aseh. רבי
עקיבא learns it from the פסוק אשם הוא. So he doesn't connect
it to this פסוק of telling me, you know, what I can
and cannot do. So according to him, we're back to the question
why you needed the פסוק. Let's take a look. רבי עקיבא אומר
אינו צריך הרי הוא אומר אשם הוא בהוייתו יהא. Rabbi Akiva omer
eino tzarich harei hu omer asham hu b'havayato yehei. You don't have
to learn it from the פסוק of רק קדשיך, you learn it
from the פסוק of אשם הוא that it does not change its
identity. Okay? By the אשם and implicitly by the חטאת. chatas So
the גמרא Gemara or not whatever, not only doesn't change its identity,
cannot be used, cannot be brought if it's not the original thing.
So the גמרא Gemara, says למה לי קרא גמרא גמירי לה כל
שבחטאת מתה באשם רועה. lama lee kra gemara gemiri lah kol shebe-chatat
metah be-asham ro'eh. We're back to our question. Why do I need
a פסוק? I have a הלכה למשה מסיני that if it's the,
you know, ולד, תמורה, whatever it is, if it can't be brought
for its original purpose, it has to graze. And again, you can't
tell me here that I need it to tell me you transgress
a positive command if you bring it, because רבי עקיבא isn't learning
it from a פסוק with a positive command. He's not learning it
from פסוק רק קדשיך אשר יהיו לך. pasuk rak kodshecha asher yihyu
lecha. He's learning it from פסוק of אשם הוא. So the גמרא
Gemara says הכי נמי, you know what? You're right. דכי אתא קרא
לדרב. de-chi ata kra le-de-Rav. The פסוק is coming to tell me
what רב Rav tells me. דאמר רב הונא אמר רב אשם שניתק
לרעייה, de-amar Rav Huna amar Rav asham she-nitak l're'iya, if an אשם
has been given over to graze, like it was handed over to
the shepherd and now it was set out to pasture, ושחטו לשם
עולה כשר. u-shechato l'shem ola kasher. If you shechted it even before
it got a blemish, and you shechted it for an עולה, olah
it actually counts as an עולה. olah. Once it was put into
that mode, once it was put into the stage of where now
putting it into the process where it's going to get a blemish
and we're going to redeem it and use it for an עולה,
olah that is enough to change its identity now. Now it's seen
as a future עולה, olah and if you actually were to shecht
it with the animal itself, not the funds it had been, you
know, not you brought some substitute animal, it didn't get a blemish,
you didn't transfer it, it's the animal itself, somehow the קדושה itself
because now it's in the process
of
קדושת עולה kedushat ola when it gets to that other animal, even
in this animal itself, it can turn it into an עולה. olah
Okay. Why?
Across the board for an אשם?
Across the board, all the time.
It's just not with any specific.
No,
no, no, it's specifically about an אשם that cannot be used for
its original purpose, like a case of a תמורה, right? A normal
אשם, no. But this אשם where the הלכה למשה מסיני is telling
me that what you're going to do is wait for it to,
right, this אשם that is a, it can't be a ולד, it's
a תמורה, it's the מתו בעליה metu ba'aleha, נתכפרו באחר, nitkapru b'acher,
this type of a thing where it cannot be coming for that
original sin, right? So therefore there's nothing to do with it
and
the
Once it just began the process and was given over to the
shepherd, its קדושה *kedusha* has now essentially transformed already. And were you
to שחט *shecht* it, it would be an עולה olah. *olah*. Okay,
so טעמא דניתק *taima denitak*, so גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, טעמא דניתק
*taima denitak*. So the reason, now that's what רב הונא אמר רב
*Rav Huna Amar Rav* teaches us. Now the reason is because it
was already handed over for pasture. הא לא ניתק לא *ha lo
nitak lo*, but if it wasn't handed over for pasture, just because
we know still it's still eventually what's going to happen, but it
hasn't somehow shift gears yet, it's still in its old state, it
hasn't somehow begun its new process, so in that case we would
not say if you שחט *shecht* it just right at the outset,
even after it became not purpose, not useful for its original purpose,
it would not be an עולה olah *olah*. דאמר קרא הוא *d'amar
kra hu*, אשם הוא *asham hu*, בהוייתו יהא *b'havayaso yehei*, it retains
that status unless you do something to change its identity. So somehow
we're saying the פסוק הוא *pasuk hu* is telling me, again we
know this idea it's very funny, right, the simple sense of Rabbi
Akiva and Rabbi Ishmael is they are learning from the פסוקים *psukim*
this idea that an אשם *asham* and a חטאת chatas *chatas* that
cannot be used for the original חטא *cheit* are basically let die
or the אשם *asham* whatever you don't bring it, you do something
else with it. The גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* is so committed to the
idea that we know all of this הלכה למשה מסיני *Halacha LeMoshe
MiSinai* both חטאת chatas *chatas* and an אשם *asham*, you'd have to
tell me that they're learning something else with these פסוקים *psukim*. So
Rabbi Ishmael is learning from these פסוקים *psukim* this דין איסור עשה
*din issur asei* and Rabbi Akiva is learning from these פסוקים *psukim*
that the אשם *asham* it stay, it has that identity, you know,
it a little bit resists changing its identity. Yes, the הלכה למשה
מסיני *Halacha LeMoshe MiSinai* tells me that once it starts a process
of being put out to pasture so it can get a מום
*mum*, so the money can be transferred, so it could be brought
as an עולה olah *olah*, once it starts that process that, what
do you call it, that then its קדושה *kedusha* has transfer, has
changed, has transformed and if you שחט *shecht* it it's an עולה
olah *olah*. But the הוא *hu* tells me it's a little resistant
to starting that process and it's only once it's handed over to
the shepherd. Before that happens if you were to שחט *shecht* it
it would still be an unusable אשם *asham* and not be כשר
*kosher*. Now I see a lot of hands I just want to
point out that there's a very large תוספות Tosfos *Tosafos* here because
there's
some interesting positions of רבנו תם *Rabbeinu Tam* about all of this.
Like רבנו תם *Rabbeinu Tam* thinks that actually this idea that you
have to wait to put it out to pasture is only דרבנן
*derabbanan* not a דאורייתא *de'oraisa*. So he has to reread this גמרא
gemara. *Gemara* because this גמרא gemara *Gemara* sounds like it's a דאורייתא
*de'oraisa* that you need it to be put out to pasture for
it to change its identity. So רבנו תם *Rabbeinu Tam* basically says
no, he like completely rewrites the גמרא *Gemara*, it's not about being
put out to pasture, it's about having specific כוונה *kavana* to make
it an עולה olah, *olah*. Like if you שחט *shecht* it even
without being put out to pasture but if you שחט *shecht* it
לשם עולה olah. *l'shem olah* it works, if you שחט *shecht* it
לשם אשם *l'shem asham* it doesn't work, that's really what makes it
change its identity not being put out to pasture and so on.
Anyway it's not the simple sense of this גמרא *Gemara* by any
means. This גמרא *Gemara* seems like it's דאורייתא *de'oraisa* that putting it
out to pasture changes its identity but רבנו תם *Rabbeinu Tam* based
on another גמרא *Gemara* wants to say that that's only rabbinic so
he has another way of reading what would be the dividing line
between those two stages. יישר כח *yashar koach*, do you have a
question Michael?
Yeah so, or I don't know if the גמרא *Gemara* is going
to do this over here so does he think that Rabbi Akiva
has a פסוק *pasuk* already and Rabbi Ishmael like, you know,
no the גמרא *Gemara* does not do that thankfully. תוספות Tosfos. *Tosafos*
does that, it's actually quite interesting. תוספות Tosfos *Tosafos* sort of says
you know if you go back and you read the ברייתא braita,
*braisa*, it doesn't sound at all like that's what they're talking about,
like Rabbi Ishmael is learning an איסור עשה *issur asei* and Rabbi
Akiva is learning this הלכה *halacha* because if that's what they were
talking about then they're like not talking to one another, they're talking
about different points. So תוספות Tosfos *Tosafos* actually says, it's actually an
interesting תוספות Tosfos *Tosafos*, he basically says well we would have to
say according to this גמרא *Gemara* that Rabbi Akiva didn't understand what
Rabbi Ishmael was saying, that Rabbi Akiva thought what Rabbi Ishmael saying
is what the ברייתא braita. *braisa* sounds like Rabbi Ishmael is saying,
that he's actually learning the real הלכה *halacha* of that a חטאת
chatas *chatas* has to be let die. So it's actually תוספות Tosfos
*Tosafos* basically points out that the problems with this read is that
it completely violates the sense of what's going on in the ברייתא
braita, *braisa*. And his basic answer is well we'd have to say
according to this גמרא *Gemara* that basically Rabbi Akiva wasn't understanding Rabbi
Ishmael. But what it really means is the גמרא *Gemara* is not
פשט *pshat* in the ברייתא braita. *braisa*. The ברייתא braita, *braisa* is
they really are learning out the basic הלכה *halacha* that a חטאת
chatas *chatas* is left to die.
Yeah and these חטאות *chatasos* according to this שיטה *shita*, right, not
necessarily
yeah
I don't know okay no no no yeah yes wherever well no
whatever wherever you are you're you know you're somewhere in the Galilee
or something yes in Tel Aviv.
Yeah I would have thought the phrase would have been ניתן לרעייה
*nittan l'ra'aya* like it was given over to grazing why it's ניתק
*nitak*?
ניתק *nitak* is because it's about changing its identity it's separated it's
removed from its original identity exactly exactly. Okay so now the גמרא
*Gemara* says like this אמר מר *amar mar* הלכה היא בנזיר *halacha
hi benazir* okay so this is back to Rabbi Yochanan's statement that
it's a special הלכה *halacha* by נזיר Nazir. *nazir* that this pile
of unspecified funds gets assigned to be an עולה olah
*olah*. ותו ליכא *ve-tu lekka*? Is it only in נזיר Nazir? *nazir*
that this הלכה *halacha* applies to like it sounds like a special
נזיר nazir *nazir* הלכה *halacha*
there are other cases that are essentially the exact same. והתניא *ve-ha
tanya* we learned in a ברייתא braita *braisa* and it teaches. ושאר
חייבי קינים Kinim שבתורה, all other we don't have to compare to
what else, but all other people that are obligated for a קינים
for bird sacrifices, which includes a classic case would be a יולדת
Yoledes would be one classic example, but basically many people that bring
קרבנות, Korbanos, often it's also on the עולה ויורד Olah V’Yored scale
where you could bring a bigger קרבן but if you don't have
enough money you bring a bird קרבן and one is a חטאת
chatas and one is an עולה. olah, So you have a person
who was obligated in these two bird sacrifices.
Okay. So, where were we? שהפרישו מעות לקיניהם. She’hafrishu ma’os l’kineihem.
They set aside money for their birds, for their this pile of
money to be used for my two birds. Okay. ורצה להביא בהן
חטאת בהמה יביא עולת בהמה יביא. V’ratza l’havi bahen chatas behema yavi
olat behema yavi.
Now what happened to them was, this is why we're talking about
the fact that they're in the עולה ויורד, Olah V’Yored, they were
on the sliding scale, is that after they set aside the money,
they came into some more money. They came, they won the lottery,
whatever, the business deal did well and now they actually have the
money, they're no longer
entitled to bring the cheaper קרבן, they have to bring the more
expensive one. So you have this pile
of unspecified funds and what you're allowed to do now is say,
well, it was for חטאת chatas. or an עולה olah, or maybe
for both, that's the interesting possibility. But what can I do with
it now that I have to bring not birds but an animal
sacrifice? Fine. I'll use it towards my animal חטאת chatas, or I'll
use it towards my animal עולה. olah. Okay. So ורצה להביא בהן
חטאת בהמה יביא עולת בהמה יביא. V’ratza l’havi bahen chatas behema yavi
olat behema yavi.
Now,
what we have to assume here as well, this gets also to
the תוספות’s Tosafot issue that he raised yesterday is: are we assuming
that this pile means that this is going to from this pile
is going to come both birds? Then it would be a big
חידוש Chiddush because then from this pile is money of a חטאת
chatas and an עולה olah, that I'm now using just for one
of them, right? Just for the animal חטאת chatas, or the animal
עולה. olah. So תוספות Tosafot is assuming no, actually what we'll assume
is we're talking about again a case where תוספות tosafos says sometimes
it only just depends on the language used. If you say, this
is for my קרבנות, Korbanos then we assume that it has both
חטאת chatas, and עולה olah money here and then you would not
be able to use it all for one. If you just say,
this is for my obligation, so then obligation could mean towards my
obligation, not for both of my קרבנות, korbanot and then you could
use it all for one and therefore the same way you could
use all of it for one bird, you can therefore now that
you're bringing bigger animals, you can use them all for one type
of a בהמה Behema and you don't have to split the money
between the חטאת chatas and the עולה. olah Okay. So that's in
that scenario. So we're going to assume the money, the pile can
be used all for one, even as birds. And that's why when
you're now buying a בהמה Behema from it, you can use it
all for one type of a בהמה. Behema. Yes?
So with birds, isn't there a thing that you can sort of
use them interchangeably once they've once you have two?
No,
you can't use them interchangeably but you don't have to designate them.
They can be you can wait to be designated until the כהן
Kohen actually slaughters them.
Right, so there's a longer period of time where they're kind of
non-specified.
Right, exactly. But again, if this pile were that clearly both birds
would come from it, even if it's not specified, if it basically
had the קדושה of חטאת chatas and an עולה olah. in it,
even in a non-specified way, you couldn't designate it all for just
a חטאת Chatat or all for an עולה. olah, That's what bothers
תוספות. So he has to say once again that this is a
case where the language you used was open-ended enough that it didn't
have to be read as you have both קרבנות korbanot here, okay?
And therefore you can use it all for one.
Now מת, Meis, let's say instead of now him coming into money,
he died. והיו לו מעות סתומים, V’hayu lo ma’os stumim, and this
money is non-specified,
יפלו לנדבה, Yiplu l’nedava, so then again it goes to an עולה.
olah, So once again you see it's exactly the הלכה by נזיר.
nazir? How does רבי יוחנן say it's only by נזיר? nazir. Now
again, I want to say and again, the same point I made
yesterday, what all this תוספות is pointing out is not really explored
in the גמרא, but תוספות says: one minute, if before he died
the pile could be used all for an עולה olah, or all
for a חטאת, Chatat it was open-ended enough, so there's not a
big חידוש Chiddush to say after he died we can do the
same thing with it. So what so again what תוספות is saying
and what the גמרא implied earlier is part of this חידוש Chiddush
that after he died you can use it you use it all
for an עולה olah, is even in a scenario where it's clear
the pile was going to be used for both. Again, that's not
stated here in the גמרא. It's not stated in the משנה. Mishnah.
But תוספות sort of is dealing with that to navigate these two
points. When it was he's alive, it says you can use it
all for a חטאת or all for an עולה. olah. So why
are you allowed to? It must be the case was that the
pile was open-ended in terms of its purpose. After he dies, yes,
but not סתומים, Stumim, סתומים Stumim in the sense of even more
open-ended, open-ended that it could be all for one. But then after
he died if there's a חידוש chiddush. that it's used for an
עולה, olah, it's not much of a חידוש chiddush if you could
have said the same thing when he was alive, right? And before
the גמרא made it clear that it understands this word סתומים Stumim
refers not just that it's not specified, but that actually both types
of monies are present. Okay. So you have to use the pile
for both types of things. So again, that's תוספות'ס Tosafot's reading this
in. I know I'm complicating this, but I just wanted to point
out that תוספות'ס Tosafot's reading that in to point out that that's
part of the חידוש. chiddush Now again, both moneys does not mean
that I said, here's my חטאת money, here's my עולה olah, money
and it got mixed up. In that case, I'm stuck. It just
means I said both the חטאת and the עולה olah. are going
to come from this pile, but I haven't designated how much for
each and so on. And there the חידוש chiddush. is that even
though there is חטאת money that is going to come from this
pile, if the guy dies, it can be used for, it's all
used towards an עולה. olah Right?
It's
a very nice way of looking at it.
Yeah. Right? Right.
Yeah.
Right. Right.
So it says רוצה להביא מן חטאת מביא מן עולה מביא, rotzeh
l'havi min chatas mevi min olah mevi, it sounds like he can
do either one, right?
Right, and that he said is not the סתומים stumim case. That's
before he died, and that was a case where he just said,
I'm going to use this for my obligation. So when he says
the generic, this is where תוספות reads it. We'll see the גמרא
actually is going to clarify a little more in this line. When
he just says generically obligation, it could be all for one, all
for the other. But if you say this is my קרבנות korbanot.
are coming from this pile and you say קרבנות korbanot, in plural,
that he says is the case of סתומים, stumim, that they're both
definitely coming from it, but you haven't designated which is which, and
in that case, the הלכה is יפלו לנדבה. yiplu l'nedavah. So anyway,
our point is is that this הלכה that we said by נזיר
nazir. is the exact same הלכה here by other things. So the
גמרא, so why do we say it's only by a נזיר? nazir?
So the גמרא says תנא נזיר וחייבי קינים דדמו ליה. tana nazir
v'chayvei kinim d'damu lei. Alright, we don't mean only a נזיר. nazir
We mean it's הלכה by everything like a נזיר. nazir Now what's
like a נזיר? nazir What's like a נזיר nazir, is that it
is one obligation that leads to multiple קרבנות. korbanot, The נזיר nazir
has three types of קרבנות, korbanot this woman let's say who's given
birth has two types of קרבנות, korbanos and there the pile therefore
even if the pile is set aside for both all of the
קרבנות korbanos because it's all derived from one obligation, there's a חידוש
chiddush. and one of those obligations happens to be an עולה olah,
that it can all go towards the עולה Olah. purpose. But if
they were two separate obligations and happened to be one pile of
money, you would not have this חידוש. What's an example of that?
The גמרא will give you an example. Let's take a look. ולאפוקי
מהא דתניא u'l'apukei mei'ha d'tanya
to exclude the following ברייתא, meaning it's only for נזיר nazir and
like this case of יולדת, yoledet, not for a case that's discussed
in the following ברייתא. ולאפוקי u'l'apukei does not mean it disagrees with
the following ברייתא, it means to distinguish it from the following ברייתא.
Often ולאפוקי u'l'apukei means it's rejecting the position of the following ברייתא,
but here it means to distinguish it from the following ruling. מי
שהיה מחוייב חטאת, mi she'haya mechuyav chatas, somebody who was obligated a
חטאת, ואמר הרי עלי עולה, v'amar harei alai olah, and in addition
to bringing a חטאת, he accepted just סתם stam an obligation of
an עולה Olah completely unrelated to his חטאת obligation, והפריש מעות, v'hifrish
ma'ot, and he set aside money, ואמר הרי אלו לחובתי, v'amar harei
eilu l'chovati, this is for my obligation. Okay, so רוצה להביא בהן
חטאת בהמה לא יביא עולת בהמה לא יביא. rotzeh l'havi bahen chatas
behemah lo yavi olat behemah lo yavi. So if he want now
what is he going to do with it? So it basically says
he cannot bring it all for חטאת and all for עולה. Olah
So here's a case, again, that goes into this case of two
types of unspecified piles. One unspecified pile where we say both funds
come from it, and one unspecified pile where you can use all
for one or all for the other. So this גמרא'ס Gemara's assuming
that because you say לחובתי l'chovati for my obligation, it means for
all of my obligations. And therefore, from this pile, both has to
come חטאת and an עולה Olah. in this case. לחובותיי. l'chovotai. לחובותיי,
l'chovotai, I guess, that's the לחובות, l'chovot, לחובותיי, l'chovotai,
לחובות שלי, l'chovot sheli, right?
No, but this is לחובותיי. l'chovotai. What would in other words are
we trying to do? Did he say for all my חובות chovot
or a specific חובה? chovah?
No, all my חובות. chovot. לחובותיי. l'chovotai. לחובות שלי. l'chovot sheli. Yeah.
Anyway, moving on. You guys can worry about the grammar. Okay, moving
on. לחובותיי. l'chovotai.
Okay, moving on.
Alright, so anyway, he said, people,
back to the גמרא. He said, he said that if this is
for my obligations plural, we'll assume that that's what he said, then
he as opposed to the case before, where the pile for the
עולה and the שלמים for the two birds, that when the woman
was alive or whatever she could redesignate it all to one or
all to the other. If you're a little bit too clear and
you mean all of my obligations, then this pile has both moneys
of a חטאת and an עולה in it. So you can't use
it all for one. Now what do you do? You don't use
it for anything? So what you basically have to do is you
basically now you could say, well, you can split it and you
get to decide how to divide it. That's what I would have
said. And then all the ברייתא here means is that you can't
use it all for one or all for the other. תוספות says
a little bit even more complicated. You have to take an animal
and you have to say however much of the money in there
is for the חטאת, it's transferred to this animal that's a חטאת.
And then you take another animal and say however much money there
is sanctified for an עולה, that קדושה is transferred to this עולה.
So that's a little funny. I would have thought if you sanctified
the pile and you didn't specify that now you can designate how
much goes for each one. Okay, but no, this is two. This
is a person who's obligated in a חטאת and also accepts an
עולה obligation. Alright, so anyway. So that's first case number one. This
person has two independent obligations, a חטאת and an עולה, set aside
a pile. It's a scenario where the language he used indicated that
that pile was both moneys in it, and because it was both
moneys in it, he cannot use it all for one or all
for the other. He has to somehow split it between the two.
Now, then of course, he goes up and he dies on us.
מת. mes. Okay, he dies. Okay, והיו לו מעות סתומין, ve-hayu lo
maos setumin, and we have this unspecified pile. Okay, and now actually
as we've already even said explicitly, it has both moneys in it.
So what do you do with it? ילכו לים המלח. yelchu le-yam
ha-melach. This case, you do not get to reuse it as an
עולה, it all has to get thrown into the ocean. Why? Because
it is not two קרבנות korbanos, that derived from one obligation, it
is two completely separate obligations that happen both to have their, you
know, this, these funds are to serve two separate קרבנות korbanos obligations,
one חטאת, one עולה. Since some of this money is a חטאת
money and you don't know how much or whatever and you can't
separate it out, you have to throw it all out, throw into
the ocean. Okay, so the הלכה בנזיר, halacha benazir, okay he's dead,
right, even if when he was alive he would be allowed to
separate out a portion, the amount, now that he's dead he can't
and you have to throw it all out. Now, so again, the
הלכה בנזיר, halacha benazir, it's not limited to a נזיר, nazir somebody
who has an obligation that leads to multiple קרבנות, korbanos, a נזיר
nazir. brings three, a יולדת yoledes brings two, and a pile of
money is set aside, even if it's designated that all of the
קרבנות korbanos, are going to come from this pile of money, if
the person dies, the money can all get used towards an עולה,
since one of those obligations is an עולה. That's the הלכה למשה
מסיני, or that's what we learn from the פסוק. But if somebody
has separate obligations and sets aside money and all of the obligations
are to come from this money, then if there's a חטאת among
them, it all has to get thrown out. Now, if it's not
a חטאת among them, let's say he had a שלמים obligation and
an עולה obligation, then there would be something to do. Then you
could go ahead and take two קרבנות, two animals and say the
שלמים money is transferred, קדושה is transferred to this animal as a
שלמים, the עולה money is transferred to this animal as an עולה.
That's not an option if one of the moneys is for a
חטאת because a חטאת that cannot be brought only has to die
and therefore the money of a חטאת that can't be brought has
to be thrown out. So there is no way of solving the
problem if it is חטאת money that's mixed up. Well, אשם would
be interesting because אשם might be able to be transferred to an
עולה, so we're going to worry about a חטאת. Okay, so let's
take a look a little bit more in the גמרא. אמר רב
אשי: amar rav ashi: הדא דאמרת מפורשים לא, hada d'amart meforashim lo,
that which you say that if the money has been designated, then
going back not to the case we said, back of like the
case of the נזיר or the case of the יולדת yoledes where
you are allowed to use the funds after the person dies towards
an עולה, or that's not allowed, that's what you have to do,
but that would only be if the pile has been non-designated. Once
the pile's been designated, you can no longer use those funds for
an עולה, right? So now we're going to try to identify what
does designated mean. Okay, so let's take a look. אמר רב אשי:
amar rav ashi: הדא דאמרת מפורשים לא, hada d'amart meforashim lo, when
you have this pile of money from this נזיר or this יולדת,
yoledes, that it's only if it's not designated.
לא תימא דאמר אלו לחטאתי ואלו לעולתי ואלו לשלמי, lo teima d'amar
elu le-chatasi ve-elu le-olasi ve-elu le-shalmi, so we're talking about a נזיר.
Don't say it's the very clear case: this is my חטאת, this
is my עולה, this is my שלמים. Obviously in that case you
cannot reuse the חטאת money for something else or even the שלמים
money for something else. Don't say it's only that case.
אלא אפילו אמר אלו לחטאתי ולעולתי ולשלמי מפורשים הן. ela afilu amar
elu le-chatasi u-le-olasi u-le-shalmi meforashim hein. So as opposed to what we've
been saying, or not opposed to, but it's now become very, very
subtle, the differences. If you say this pile is for all my
קרבנות, then it's considered non-designated,
which is which. And the guy dies or the vow is annulled
or whatever might happen, and you get to use it all for
an עולה. But if the person says this pile is for my
חטאת, עולה, and שלמים, and doesn't say which is for which, because
he specifically or she specifically identified חטאת, עולה, and שלמים, that's deemed
that the חטאת identity has been made more concrete. And now that
it's been made more concrete, the money cannot be used for an
עולה. Okay? So the special הלכה that a non-designated pile can be
used for an עולה is only if the person has not concretely
said my חטאת is coming from this. All right, that's his חידוש.
Now the גמרא says a similar point. ואיכא דאמרי, ve-ika d'amri, some
say, אמר רב אשי: amar rav ashi: לא תימא עד דאמר אלו
לחטאתי ולעולתי ולשלמי, lo teima ad d'amar elu le-chatasi u-le-olasi u-le-shalmi, not
only do you have to say that, that would make it so
concrete that you could not use this money for an עולה, אלא
אפילו אמר אלו לחחובתי הרי הן כמפורשים. ela afilu amar elu le-chovati
harei hein ke-meforashim.
This is for my obligation. That's like explicit. So then it becomes,
so what's the case that's not explicit? Right? So that's what תוספות
figures out. So maybe the only case now that's not explicit is
if you say like this is for somehow לנזירותי? li-nezi rusi? How
is that really so much different than saying this is for my
חובה? chova? And if the difference is, is that in one case
it's open-ended enough that it can all go towards one קרבן and
חובתי. chovati. anyway, implies all of my קרבנות *Korbanot*, so then there's
very little חידוש *Chiddush* left in this הלכה *Halacha*, because if the
way you sanctify this pile was that you could use all the
money towards any one, then it's not such a big חידוש *Chiddush*
that after the guy dies that it can all be used for
an עולה *Olah*. Because even when he was alive it could all
be used for only one. So once we say that that's considered
מפורשים *Mefurashim*, it's not so clear what is the case where you
have חטאת *Chatat* money mixed up and can still be used, you
know, in potential חטאת *Chatat* money mixed up that can still be
used towards an עולה *Olah*. Yes, Michael.
Yeah. It says, you know, I'm putting in, I take three different
coins, right? He says, these three of these are going to be
used for some עולה *Olah*, חטאת *Chatat*, and whatever, right? So why
can't we take one of the coins and say, well, at least
one of them was meant to be an עולה *Olah* and pick
that? You think what, like the money itself is like each one
is a little bit of חטאת *Chatat* in it?
Wait one more time, what's the question?
If you put in like whatever it is, you put in 100
bucks, right,
why can't we just leave over just one dollar, one dollar? Yeah,
I was wondering about that. I guess it's because we don't ultimately
know like which dollar it is and we're not able to designate
which dollar. Yeah, exactly. We're not able to designate which dollar. Okay.
Anyway, if you want to see תוספות *Tosafot* try to explain what
the difference is, let me find the right line in תוספות *Tosafot*.
Alright.
Okay,
so if you take a look, it is five lines down in
the wide lines where it says הגה *Hagah*, like after two dots
on the wide lines of תוספות *Tosafot*. He says which תוספות *Tosafot*?
The תוספות *Tosafot* הא דאמרת *Hadata Amarta*. Go five lines down in
the wide lines where the whole wide lines of תוספות *Tosafot* begins,
the middle of the line, הגה *Hagah*. איכא דאמרי כי אמר לחובתי
נמי כמפורשים בתערובת הוו פירוש אחרי אמר מלך דלחובתי משמע לכל חובתי
בין לחטאת בין לעולה וסתומים דיפלו לנדבה היינו כי אמר לקרבנות נזירותי
דחמר לקרבנות נזירותי טפי מחובתי שלא פירש חטאת בהן מכל מקום משמע
נמי דלכל קרבנות קאמר *Ika d'amri, ki amar l'chovati nami k'mefurashim b'tarovet
havei. Pirush acharei, amar melech, d'lchovati mashma l'chol chovati, bein l'chatat bein
l'olah. U'stumim d'yiplu l'nedava hainu ki amar l'korbanot nezirotai, d'chamar l'korbanot nezirotai
t'fei me'chovati shelo peirash chatat bahen. Mikol makom mashma nami d'lchol korbanot
ka'amar.* Right, if it meant any one of the קרבנות *Korbanot* it
wouldn't be a חידוש *Chiddush* at all, then you can use the
whole pile obviously for one thing. So somehow when you say קרבנות
*Korbanot* and it means all the קרבנות *Korbanot*, that's not מפורשים *Mefurashim*.
Okay. ולא היה יכול להביא בכולן קרבן אחד *V'lo haya yachol l'havi
b'chulan korban echad.* So even though there it also meant all the
קרבנות *Korbanot* and you couldn't have used it for one thing, but
that is not enough מפורשים *Mefurashim*. But if you somehow say חובתי
*Chovati*, that's already more מפורש *Mefurash* and it's considered like the חטאת
*Chatat* is more concrete and you can't misuse it. Don't ask me,
I don't understand how these are really different. All right.
Yes, but it's talking about in other words this particular coin. In
other words, it's like very concrete, correct? In other words, money is
usually value and so the value could be this for this or
for that, so they actually it's like a one-to-one correspondence, this coin
was meant for this חטאת *Chatat*, this coin for that, and they
don't know which one is which. Right, that's like the issue. And
in other words, because a pile of coins is symbolic of general
value.
Yeah, but when you sanctify coins, it's you know, if this coin
was sanctified as a חטאת *Chatat*, I can't just say well it
just meant I was giving money for a חטאת *Chatat* and I'm
going to give different money. No, it's very concretely this coin.
Really concrete, exactly, exactly, the whole object of the coin is like
a piece of the animal.
Exactly, exactly. Okay, let's just read one more line. So anyway what
we do see here is, it's a, it's not limited to נזיר
*Nazir*, it applies to other things where multiple obligations arise from one
thing. There's a case where it's something is so non-specified that even
when the person is alive, they can use the pile towards all
of one קרבן *Korban*. There's other cases where it's not specified but
it's clear multiple קרבנות *Korbanot* have to come from it. That's the
חידוש *Chiddush* that even in that case where multiple קרבנות *Korbanot* have
to come from it, if it can't be used, the person dies,
other types of things happen, it gets to all go for an
עולה *Olah*. But then there's a case where somehow the fact that
there's a חטאת *Chatat* here has been said so concretely that even
though it's not specified yet, it still can't be used for an
עולה *Olah*. So the clear example is the person just said explicitly
חטאת *Chatat*, עולה *Olah*, and שלמים *Shelamim* are coming from here. The
other case gets much more vague what the exact line of distinction
is. But the חידוש *Chiddush* is even if it's all, it's still
not specified which is which, once חטאת *Chatat* has been labeled explicitly,
it can now not be used for an עולה *Olah*. Let's do
one more line here of רבא *Rava* and finish this עמוד *Amud*.
אמר רבא הא דאמרינן מותרי סתומים stumim. יפלו לנדבה *Amar Rava, ha
d'amrinan motrei stumim yiplu l'nedava*, when we say that the non-specified pile
goes for an עולה *Olah*, אם הפריש דמי חטאת מביניהם הרי הן
כמפורשים *Im hifrish d'mei chatat mibeineihem harei hen k'mefurashim*. Listen to this
interesting הלכה *Halacha*. Let's say I separated out this pile, this pile
is going to be for my, for my קרבנות *Korbanot* for my
נזיר *Nazir*. Okay, I'm a woman, and I separate this out because
my husband's about to annul the vow. But before he does, I
separate out this pile. And then I say you know what I'm
going to take this amount of this money and this will be
for my חטאת *Chatat*. And then this pile now is left with
basically being עולה *Olah* and שלמים *Shelamim* money. Since something has been
made concrete from that pile, we don't say oh well the rest
is... Even better, there’s no חטאת money in here at all, so
now if my husband annuls the vow, certainly we can use it
all for an עולה. That would be the logical thing to say.
Even better, you took the חטאת money out. No. Now that I’ve
made one piece of that pile concrete, it’s like the whole pile
has become more concrete and less, you know, this is all sort
of like, you know, what was it, Heisenberg uncertainty principle? Like, you
know, its whole identity hasn’t yet formed yet when it’s סתומים. So
then we can sort of like form it. But once there’s something
has been made concrete about it, so either the חטאת part’s made
concrete about it, now it’s, now it’s come more into the real
world, and now it cannot be, you know, re-identified. So even in
that case,
what happens to the עולה and שלמים?
Then the money has to be divided between an עולה and a
שלמים. Whether it’s divided 50/50, exactly what you do with it, but
it doesn’t all go with an עולה. It now has stopped living
in that completely, you know, amorphous, non-real world of indeterminate identity. Since
part of it has been given a determined identity, the whole thing
has become more, more concrete, and therefore cannot be redefined. Okay, so
we will end with that for.